before we
begin tonight program we would like to
again welcome everyone who arrived to
the a today for the Advan course and for
the how to teach over the children
course that starts
tomorrow and uh all the staff of the
organization who gathered here together
for these courses tonight we begin a new
program the program is called what is
Nirvana and how do we get there and this
program will be presented by GHA M roach
and I would like to introduce GHA M
roach he's the first Wester to have been
awarded the degree of guip or master of
Buddhism after more than 20 years of
study in tibetan monasteries
he has used this training to become a
prominent International teacher
philanthropist author and educator g m
roach graduated with honors from
Princeton University and has received a
presidential scholar medal from the
president of the United States at the
White House he help found andin
International Diamond Corporation and
bringing to annual sales of over $100
million donating his profits to
International Aid projects his book
about achieving business and personal
Success Through generosity The Diamond
Cutter has become a global bestseller in
20 languages he's the founder of the
Asian classic Institute diamond mountain
university the Asian classic input
project world view the yoga Studies
Institute star in the east Global family
Refugee Aid three jewels community
outreach centers and The Diamond Cutter
Institute and there is so much more but
this is just a brief biography of his
amazing uh life and activities and uh
most importantly he has been coming here
for um for over 10 years now and this is
a great honor for us to have him here
again and always beautiful inspiring
teaching so this week is going to be
about Nirvana let us welcome gu
[Applause]
[Music]
p
Oh
Come and Rome
[Music]
captiv and
morning the
[Music]
ex until the Son of
God appear
[Music]
rej
rej in
my
[Music]
new shall come to
thee Oh Come th Day Spring
from and Che Us by your
[Music]
dispers
The
Cloud of
light and death star
Shadows
to
rejo
Rejoice
the shall come to the oh
[Music]
w
Oh Come desire
ofs
find in one the hearts of
all
kind oh our son
division
SE and be yourself the
king of
Peace
Rejoice
IMU shall come to the
[Music]
ho Oh Come Oh Come
my and ransome
[Music]
captive
and only
[Music]
ex until the Son of
God
Rejoice rejoice
IM shall come to
the
[Music]
oh for
okay
all uh so did everybody get a
notebook yeah don't look at
it later if you want to take notes you
can um
so I don't know I grew up like most of
you uh I grew up in in the United States
in Arizona and um I used to hear the
word Nirvana sometimes like people would
say that feels like Nirvana I'd like to
go to Nana you know there was a rock
band named for not
Nirvana and uh there was a restaurant
where I live named
Nana and uh I don't know I had two ideas
about
I think one
was was that uh when you went there you
disappeared right like they say you went
to Nirvana and you can you don't know
where he is anymore he just disappeared
you know like that that was one idea
that was when I was a child that they'd
say go to Nirvana and you just finished
and you're gone and that's all the other
idea was
uh uh like one of those restaurants like
you would go there and you would start
eating and you would stay there
forever uh just enjoying the food you
know or something like that like you go
to Nirvana and you're just in some place
and it had two meanings when I was
growing up one was that you pisted out
and one was that you don't do anything
else you just stay there
forever and like a very good uh
marijuana or something you and uh that
was that was what I heard about Marana
when I was a kid then uh you know I
ended up studying in in Tibet mon
and uh one of the books one of the first
books we had to study for 12 years uh
had a
beautiful explanation of nirvana in it a
very beautiful uh teaching on Nirvana so
uh when I was when we were talking about
my coming here this year I thought oh
that would be nice to to translate it
and um and maybe share it with everybody
because it's a very beautiful teaching
on NADA and um it answered a lot of
questions for me and I think most
importantly it made Nirvana something
that I could reach and it made Nirvana
something that I wanted to reach because
it was kind of scary to think about
Nana's just I Disappeared you know and
where would I be after that and how
could I enjoy it if I wasn't here and uh
you know
I I was I think this teaching is very
beautiful presentation of Nirvana
because it makes Nirvana something
relevant to your life and it's not some
strange thing that's going to happen to
you in 43 years if you're lucky uh it's
something if you understand Nirvana and
if you have a good teaching on N it's
something you can start doing now uh
it's some
practical thing that you can use now and
you can start uh working towards your
nana building your nana so you know the
more teaching I got on Nirvana the more
I thought I could do it you know and
that it would be fun and I wouldn't
disappear it'd actually be pretty cool
for all my friends
too uh so we're going to go through Nana
that way and then I thought every night
at the end um I thought one thing I'll
I'll I'll leave you with a little
meditation you can do uh there are some
meditations you can do that would bring
you closer to
the and that would be one thing and then
I think uh maybe the last 10 minutes if
anybody has any questions uh about what
I say uh or your own idea about Nirvana
so 10 minutes before we stop I'll give
you a little uh meditation you can do
about Nana and then
um and then you can ask some questions
so save up your questions in your mind
all right as we go so I guess I like to
start with words I love words and I like
to talk about the word Nirvana and what
is where did it come from uh you know
what are the parts of the word so n is
is n Sans word
say you have to C your tongue back I was
telling if you Cur your tongue back then
you
soundly
say
yeah uh L comes from n okay n um means
uh down or away or not okay and before V
it has to change to R so it becomes an N
VA is a Sanskrit roote all Sanskrit is
built around roots and there it has
three distinct different meanings V can
mean three totally different things and
each one is appropriate for
Nirvana uh so for example I I'm studying
Chinese Buddhism and uh nowadays and one
of my teachers said we chose not to
translate the word they call
nepan uh they didn't translate the word
nirada because they knew van had three
different meanings and they didn't want
to leave one out so they decided to just
keep it as the okay so V can mean three
different things uh and then Anna is an
ending that means U something that gets
you there so nits out the first meaning
is to blow so
NVA uh means to blow out like to blow
out a candle
or to to stop a fire to extinguish a
fire is nirvana uh so Nirvana is is seen
as uh stopping a fire or like blowing
out of fire okay and what is the fire
and then there are a lot of ideas about
what the fire is there are many many
ideas but uh I think the one that's the
correct one is said to be uh is your
claas okay your we have them in yoga
right
it these five uh negative emotions okay
bad emotions that we have you can say
jealousy uh
anger uh desire we we divide desire into
good desire and bad desire good desire
is desire for ice
cream uh bad desire is desire to uh have
an ice cream at the expense of someone
else okay uh same object same emotion
different intention right so uh like
Swami G was saying
[Music]
today or the day before yeah sorry I
conf uh so Nirvana is to blow out the
the ultimate definition of nirvana in
that we have to memorize is uh I'll say
I I'll say it with you
say Mal
you guys are
sleep Tang this the definition of uh we
have definitions perly uh so means the
obstacles caused by your negative
emotions malupa means all of them bang
means to eliminate them forever s Tango
means based on
your perceiving the meaning of reality
okay so based on you perceiving the true
nature of reality you are able because
of that to remove your negative emotions
forever right and what I would say is um
at this point okay I think we'll do it
now instead of at the end okay i' find
it useful when talking about Nirvana
right now before we go on try TR to
think of the negative emotion you have
that makes your life most unhappy okay
like everybody has a favorite it's like
ice cream okay everybody has their own
I'll tell you mine okay freely uh which
is jealousy okay like if uh somebody
says I heard a good buddist teacher and
yeah it doesn't matter if it's not me I
immediately get jealous I didn't have to
hear their name yet you know I start
worrying about them hoping that I won't
be in Arizona anytime soon you know or
you know like that like right away and
it goes with everything everything I do
it infects so you know everybody has
their own uh specialty you have your own
favorite negative emotion or we say you
wouldn't be here okay that emotion was
probably quite instrumental in bringing
you into a world which is impermanent
where you are mortal where you will
suffer and where you will die okay so
the
the special negative emotion that you
have I don't know what's your specialty
mine is jealousy but you can assume that
it also helped get you here in into the
world of suffering like uh it had a big
part to play in your being here which
means if someone is here in this room
and if you're not a a disguised DEA or
you know High Yogi like uh what is
thata in the they say he sto wanding
around he still wondering the world if
you're not like correction or uh if you
are not a hidden Angel right then be
then you're here only because you have
you still have those emotions and they
they the karma of having that emotion
thrust you into this life and it will
kill
you yeah it does kill you yeah
uh the karma of it kills you so we all
have so I would encourage you as we go
through the talk you know like your
first meditation assignment for tonight
is just to try to try to re recognize or
try to identify what is your own uh
worst uh mental Affliction you know what
is your own worst claa Your Own Worst
negative emotion because we all have one
if you're not a disguised uh you know
Buddha or something then you have one
you have we say
84,000 uh it's very famous g means
84,000 and we have it we all have it uh
we we have 84,000 variations on negative
emotions within the human mind and then
that's why Buddha is said to have taught
uh
84,000 groups of scriptures each one to
address a different negative emotion so
out of those
84,000 uh which one is it that you have
okay like try to identify it how will
you
know when you're having it uh you'll be
unhappy all right that's allong uh
claa a negative emotion which is called
it has its own definition
too which
is uh
means the person who has
it their own
mind is uh
Disturbed uh SE by this mental function
by this by this thought okay so what is
a
Nirvana In the High School uh is to
remove your own negative emotions
permanently uh by applying your your
Vidya
your your knowledge of of reality and
then uh a negative emotion is defined as
any thought which upsets your peace of
mind all right so if you want to know if
youve reached nirvana yet or
not uh you would just see if anything
was a was capable of disturbing your
piece of mind if there's a thought in
your mind which would disturb your peace
of mind that's a that's a negative
emotion and you have it and and Nirvana
it's a very beautiful thing uh Nirvana
would be to blow out
nerva that those negative emotions
forever all right and they they're very
careful to distinguish between
suppressing a negative emotion and and
destroying it uh forever okay so that's
a beautiful thing about nirv Nirvana is
we'll discuss that uh if we have time
we'll go in into whether it's possible
to uh drop out of the state of Nana and
come back to having a dist mind uh but
uh if you achieve a real Nirvana then
you you it's not possible to have a
negative thought again okay and and just
try to we'll be we'll be doing different
exercises to try to see what that would
feel like but I think right now in your
own mind uh you can imagine what it
might feel like if you never got upset
again in your whole life if it was incap
if you were incapable of getting upset
or angry or wanting a third ice cream
from the B I'm talking the same night
okay uh you know then then that that's
what Nirvana would feel like okay
there's another meaning of nirva Nirvana
and um this is very beautiful it's very
difficult uh
it's a long a VA and it means to weave
something uh typ leave weave a piece of
cloth or weave a piece of fa Fabric and
often times uh in Sanskrit when you do
something repeatedly or when you need to
do something over and over again to to
do that thing they they repeat the root
so it' be va va like Lady Gag
GA but it would be vaa okay and then
then uh that came into English as as as
VI which came into weave okay so
V means to weave uh a piece of fabric
right and uh in that sense Nirvana was
spoken by the Buddha in in um there's a
book called The Sutra of the great
Nirvana and in there he said uh Nana
means N means un and VA means to weave
and n means to unweave the illusion so
we have woven an illusion around our our
minds our minds are caught in a web of
Illusion and then ner nerva means to
unweave or
Unravel uh that illusion okay so really
the two meanings of Nirvana that we have
so far one is a cause and one is an
effect right uh if you can
unweave uh the if you can come to
understand uh reality then you can blow
out your mental afflictions your your
negative thoughts and if you
cannot we say in in the Buddhist schools
if you are not able to grasp how reality
is really working then you it's not
possible to stop your anger or your
jealousy or any other emotion forever
it's it cannot
happen they feed on your
misunderstanding of things okay so you
cannot reach uh it's not possible to
reach nirvana if you still have a with
you if you still misunderstand things
around you so you know I like to speak
practically I have to talk to a lot of I
don't know we just got back from China
and you know it's not like they're into
spiritual things right now I mean they
spent I don't know the last how many
years UH 60 years under under you're
told not to think spiritually so to get
up in a in China and just say let's
meditate you know uh it doesn't work out
uh and you have to go really basic and
you have to really speak you know
practical and uh maybe that's better
anyway I don't know uh so what would it
mean to misunderstand your world right
and how would that cause a mental a
negative emotion you see so Swami G
talked about
it was it today or no it's yesterday it
was definitely yesterday uh he was
talking about somebody hurting us
somebody uh doing injury to us yelling
at us right and then uh what should we
do back and he said that the most
foolish thing uh you could do would be
to return the insult or return the
injury because
uh where the person where's the person
come from why has a person come to you
to injure you why has a person come to
you to insult
you you according to these ideas you
must have done it to someone before
there's no question okay it's not
possible uh to meet someone who's uh
doing you injury unless you have done a
similar injury to someone else in in
China you
say uh
if you plant a if you see a watermelon
there must have been a watermelon seed
there's not a it doesn't take a
philosopher uh to to understand that
okay if you see a big watermelon and she
and somebody tells you asks you where
did it come from then you say well a
watermelon seed and then they say well
did you see that and you say no but you
don't have to I mean all watermelons
come from watermelon if I see a
watermelon there must have been a seed
before that's all it doesn't and it must
have been a watermelon seed and not a
mango seit cuz that's the way it works
okay so if you meet a person uh who
insults you or hurts you it can it's
like a watermelon and it it must have
come from a seed and it must have been
something you did and it must have been
the same and that's all if a person uh
approaches you and and insult you calls
you stupid then it means you you did
something similar to somebody else
before that's all okay it came from the
same seat that's
all so as swam G said so beautifully
last night what's the stupidest thing
you could do to someone who calls you
stupid call him stupid back huh call him
stupid back yeah to call him stupid back
would be the stupidest thing you could
do if someone called you stupid actually
it would prove that they're
right I think right would prove that
they are correct uh and then human
nature why would you call it human
nature I like that human nature is to
respond and it's to it's to respond in
kind right if someone's violent to us
we're violent back if someone calls me
stupid then I call him stupid back and
and that's sansar
okay like we always talking about
sansara and then sansara feels like some
kind of place like New
Jersey okay and
uh now I met the dama like 30 years ago
I said what should I do with my life he
said study with G I said where is he he
said New
Jersey um so s is not like a
Sara is not like a place okay Sara is
the perpetuation
of of pain of suffering okay SAR is the
perpetuation of suffering how do you
perpetuate it's a circle a downward
cycle how do you perpetuate that Circle
someone calls you stupid uh you call
them stupid back and then they
return again to call you stupid and
that's just that's Sun okay it's not
we'll talk about it later but it's not
really a place it's a condition that we
tend to do what exactly the kind of
thing that causes more trouble for
ourselves that's what we do all day
that's what we do so to not understand
that
uh is to weave uh a web around yourself
that's VA and near vaah means you can
stop stop it right Nirvana means uh
unravel the web of Illusion that you
have built around yourself okay that's
the real meaning of Nan and then you
will get to the first meaning of Nan
which
is to blow it out to blow out your
negative emotions right okay so you have
to have the first kind of nerve to get
to the second kind of n you have to
unravel the way you see things and then
that would allow you to stop your
negative emotions how why in the case of
a person who comes up to you and calls
you
stupid um what would it mean to unravel
the
situation how could you think about
it it's a
what you'd say oh this person came from
something I did before okay right that
would be unraveling the situation
someone came up you call you stupid
unraveling the situation Vidya knowledge
understanding would be to think oh this
person has come from me I created this
person okay just that thought I created
this person how would that affect your
anger for example if you're right by
tomorrow you got to tell me your your
favorite negative emotion all right I
confessed mine I mean I could go into it
but it's
embarrassing
uh like I'm going to ask you to tomorrow
I'm going to like ask five people but
suppose yours is anger okay which
doesn't happen to be mine I'm lucky I
rather have jealousy and anger but
uh but suppose it's anger okay suppose
your problem is anger how would anger be
affected uh in a situation where someone
called you stupid if you had your mind
firmly on the fact that they are coming
from you calling somebody else
to would you where would your anger go
where does anger fit in
there you're angry at yourself you're
angry at yourself maybe you could be
angry at yourself but could you be angry
at them I don't think it's possible you
created them they are like a it's like
spitting in the mirror you know like you
don't like what you see in the mirror
you know it's not the mirror's
SP it's you okay no really when you uh
when you say back to a person you're
stupid are spitting in the mirror
because they are just reflecting what
you did last week they are you are
seeing who you are you know in AR little
University uh I love it there's a lot of
half
sentences people are
constantly speaking half sentences you
know somebody will say jig you're really
stupid you know and she'll go but you're
really because the implication is that
whenever you seeing someone else is you
is what you were last week so you know
you sit down with somebody and you want
to explain to them why this person in
the AL is really irritating and why they
always other people and why
they're always stupid and then everyone
in the table is smiling and ning your
head all
irritating doesn't speaks at the wrong
time yeah yeah yeah and they're agreeing
with you you know and suddenly you
realize they're they're saying yeah
that's how you
act really I I mean I'm just saying we
can study a scripture we will study
scripture but I just told you the whole
thing okay like it's good to have the
scripture but um that's the whole thing
it's not possible to be angry at a
person who calls you stupid if you truly
understand that they are reflecting what
you did last week okay and it's not them
who's
stupid and that's all and then the
emotion of anger cannot arise in your
mind by thinking this way in time you
reach
Nana and that's Nana so I have a
question for you when you reach nirvana
would you
disappear according to this
idea
no right it's not your body that's
causing a problem right it's it's it's
not bad when you reach there's no reason
to say that your body disappears when
you reach nirvana okay could could 10
people in this room right now which
Swami G also mentioned last night have
reached nirvana
already could 10 people in this room
have reached nirvana already
yeah would they necessarily appear to
you as
peaceful no it just what you see depends
on what you put in your mind you see I
mean everybody in this room could have
achieved nada except get
Mich and he wouldn't even know you see
cuz they were just act like normal
people cuz he has seeds in his mind to
see them that way even when they're not
okay got it like they're already totally
peaceful already they reached Nana
already they did
n they they stop their negative emotions
but he keeps seeing reflections of his
own behavior in them which are not part
of them he's he's throwing these
Reflections on them and then he sees
them acting how he acts and not how they
see themselves acting it's possible like
I had people argue with me they said no
that's not possible that everybody in
this room reached new rone already I
said why not and they said well they
would be acting very peacefully I said
why and they said well they wouldn't
have any CLS they wouldn't have any
negative emotions they would be sweet
and thoughtful they would never be angry
they would always give you the ice cream
you know
right okay uh and and but everybody's
not like that you see then people give
the argue with me no no I don't think
more than one or two people in this room
could have achieved maybe some of
me which
okay maybe he did but but not those
other people they're they're too unkind
or they're too
irritable uh to have reach H okay but we
wouldn't we wouldn't be able to see you
see because we only seeing how we were
before and we don't know how they're
seeing themselves and we don't know how
they think of themselves okay so it is
possible that uh many people in this
room have achieved uh Nirvana already
and and we wouldn't know because we our
mind keeps throwing up these images
that reflect how we are and and we never
see how they see themselves all
right which brings me to the third
meaning of of the the word Nirvana okay
so V there's three roots in
Sans uh the third one also is v n van uh
which means to uh conquer or to defeat
and you find it in English in the word
Vish or Invincible okay
uh it means to destroy it means to
destroy or to to win a battle against
somebody
okay in the word so the word nirvan the
three roots of the word nirvan are meant
to be are meant to be thought of in
order okay first is I would like to blow
out my favorite negative emotion which
for me is jealousy okay and then
secondly how you going to do that you
have to unravel you have to unweave the
way you see things you think the person
is calling you stupid because they're
stupid but they're calling you stupid
because you called someone stupid last
week and if you don't understand that
then you're stupid okay and you have to
unwe that idea that they are coming from
their side okay that's the second
meaning of buun and then the third one
is what if you can unravel the way you
see other
people and thereby blow out your
negative emotions then you
have won the war okay and you have won
the war and those are the three meanings
of n those are the three uh roots that
you see in the word uh n okay then when
you uh restart in in Sanskrit they call
you arat okay someone who reaches
Nirvana is called
Arad uh in in Buddhism okay
AR mean it can mean to kill somebody
uh and hut hut can mean the same as Han
can mean the same as hin as in
a
a okay ar ar means enemy means to strike
what's anah
it's the heart name of the heart chakra
but why yeah unstruck nobody ever beat
it so heart means to strike a means very
much un means
not means your heart beats without
anyone using a stick on it that's why
the chakra here is called the unstuck
sound it's beating it's like a drum but
nobody had to use a stick on it on okay
so our
means uh someone who has destroyed the
enemy so arat means a person who has
reached n right we call them enemy
destroyers in in Buddhism they're called
enemy destroyers that makes the enemy
who your own negative emotions okay my
jealousy is my enemy and then uh if I
can destroy it I become in and then I've
reached NADA so I have a question for
you I don't know what I'm going to talk
about for four more days cuz I'm using
it all
up
uh that's
okay uh are Enlightenment and Nirvana
the same thing if you reach nirvana are
you a Buddha or are you in
life what do you think because I know
when I was growing up a lot of people
with say Nirvana and Enlightenment on
the same thing but now I think you can
guess that what
not the same thing all right NADA is
less Enlightenment is more all right
people can can and do reach nirvana okay
uh they remove their negative emotions
within their mind forever but there's
still not a being who can appear on a
billion planets and help people you see
what I mean that's a different
skill so you can become a you can reach
nirvana relatively easily right you can
stop your negative emotions in this LA
but then to become an enlightened being
is is a big jump that's still a big jump
after that and that's uh for us the
definition of enlightened being would be
someone who could for example show
themselves in many countries on Earth at
the same time and help people you see I
mean they would have to have the ability
and it's a spontaneous ability they
don't have to think about it uh
automatically while they're asleep while
they are brushing their teeth while they
are
swimming in the ocean off Paradise
Island uh they are their their bodies
are flying out from them and showing
themselves on countless Worlds at the
same time they can be having a
conversation with you in the boutique
and at the same time they are appearing
on countless planets and helping people
in different bodies and that ability is
only had by an enlightened being so
Nirvana uh is is a lot
earlier uh than than Enlightenment okay
so that's
uh that's a basic difference between uh
NADA and Enlightenment how about uh did
you hear the word
Arya in Buddhism Ian
Arya Arya means do you know what is Arya
what is
Arya you guys thr around all these words
that we don't know either it's like now
they'll say this is a CH this is a Swami
this is a and we're
like I thought they're
anyway uh like they're different right I
assume
uh and and and in and in in this
teaching on Nirvana uh you have to be
able to distinguish between an Arya an
ARA and an enlightened being okay so so
what is an Arya okay what do Arya mean I
mean Hitler used it for a very bad
purpose he took it from Sanskrit and it
it meant Superior being uh but Arya
means someone who has seen Ultimate
Reality directly okay so they have had
an experience in Buddhism Arya means uh
someone who has had a direct experience
of Ultimate Reality okay I W I don't
know should we do that now
I'll just start
okay and let's just go to China and talk
and talk what do you call it nuts and
Bulls all right not not big philosophy
let's just talk normal English Okay
normal stuff
uh when somebody calls you stupid ready
this is a you're about to become an ARA
okay when which she takes a billion
lifetimes okay you're lucky uh
if uh someone calls come up to you and
call you stupid
right is there a person there be wake up
a little bit you took flights
today it's
hot is there a person standing there
calling you
stupid okay there is
um are they
real they are real I mean
if they weren't real you wouldn't hear
anything they're real they're there
they're calling you stupid they are real
okay I if they punch you your nose will
break that's
real am I right I it's not unreal in
that sense it's not unreal
um try to get this feeling is there a
person standing in front of you calling
you stupid who has not come from
you I say it again is there a person
standing in front of you calling you
stupid who has not come from you
no so how much did the does the person
calling you stupid who doesn't come from
you
exist
huh I'll say it again how much does a
person who has not come from you calling
you stupid
exist not no you can say zero in
Sanskrit zero is
sh okay sh that's on it means zero I'll
say it again somebody's standing there
in your face and they are calling you
stupid and and you have this emotion
comes up where you hate the person
calling you stupid but the person you're
focusing on that you hate do they exist
or not no they don't exist you see is is
there a person calling you stupid yes
yes
yes there's a person calling you stupid
and that's real is there a person call
you stupid who's not coming from
yourself which I'm going to ask you the
the person that you hate at that moment
the person that you dislike at that
moment is that the person who really is
there or is that the person who's
calling you stupid who didn't come from
you I'll say again somebody calls you
stupid you get mad you hate them you
feel bad your heart I don't know about
you I get sort of a a little pain over
here I don't know why I hate I'm hating
them at that moment I'm angry so the
person I'm angry at I'm giving you two
choices this is a diamond deal all
right is it the person who's really
there calling you stupid that you're
angry at okay or is it the
person who's not coming from
you which one are you mad
at coming you're mad at the one who's
not coming from you if he thought he was
coming from you you I don't think you'd
be angry at him am I right there's this
thing I told you before but it's
okay maybe some people weren't there
yeah you know
most of my life I spend in ashrams or
monasteries or places where you don't
have your own bathroom right and
uh true that's maybe the definition of
an
as so
uh you know you go in and I don't know a
lot of Ops I mean they're cold they're
really cold they're not like here
they're really cold and you know you're
supposed to be a good Monk and you're
not supposed to have a lot of things
we're only allowed to have two sets of
Monk's clothes so then uh you have one
good pair of wool socks
normally you know and uh then you're
going to take a shower and you walk into
the bathroom right in your one pair of
wool socks on a really cold day and then
uh suddenly they're soaked the bottom is
soaked you know and you're in Ireland or
something and they're not going to dry
out for a
week and uh and then you feel there's
this emotion you feel and you just I
don't know you feel really angry but
you're not sure who it is
yet you're really upset at somebody but
no it's real this is real life right
your socks are ruined your feet are
going to be cold for a couple days no
matter what you can wear them they'll be
warm warm
soggy or you can try to dry them out
and then they'll smell bad in a couple
days and uh so then you feel
really I don't know what do you call it
the the object of your anger isn't clear
yet you're not quite sure who it is here
but you're angry already and then
there's like three people in the AR who
use that bathroom and you know you walk
into that these are people you know they
take a shower and I don't know why they
leave the curtain open it's like some
kind of statement or or some kind of
special
practice I don't know but they can't
close the the shower I don't know what
it is or or they towel off they step out
of the shower and get the water all over
and and they draw themselves off there
out of the out of the shower like can't
you
just put the towel and dry yourself and
I'm in this bed it out uh
so either one they they either leave the
curtain open or
they or when they're soaking they they
step out in front of the sink and they
slowly dry off but they make sure a lot
of water goes on the
floor and then uh so you know I've had
this experience you you go to breakfast
at the Ash and you're
like you're like looking for these three
people down them they're all
and you're like you're like okay just
tell me who it
is I'm not going to get angry told us we
can't
get just just confess be honest who who
was it you know they're like why and
you're like just tell me who took a
shower this morning like it must have
been early it must have been like who
took a shower between 3 and five mons
just just
confess and I I won't do anything
then they like look at each other and
they're like did you take a
shower they look at you and they say
didn't you get up this morning you were
up kind of early you you said you you
know what I mean and then you realize it
was
you and you got up really early show and
you were so tired you didn't Clos the
shower curtain and then you got water
all over the bath and then you you you
stepped on it at 9:00 in your wol socks
you know 5 hours later and then suddenly
you realize it was
yourself can you still be angry at
them can you still be angry at them no
is there anyone else who put water on
the floor
no there's what you're telling me what
you just said is there's no other person
who put water on the floor am I
right can you get mad at another person
for putting water on the floor if they
are not the person who put the water on
the
floor but then try to get try to get a
handle on this
person who's yelling at you who's not
you is try get your hand try to get your
mind around the idea that the last
person who insulted you was a direct
reflection of yourself and not
them you see what I mean you the last
time you got angry at someone who said
something harsh to you or harmful
hurtful hurt your feelings the last time
someone hurt your feelings with
something that said and you felt angry
or bad towards them you were feeling bad
towards something that didn't
exist there was no such person who who
hurt you who wasn't coming from you got
it there was no such person who hurt you
who was not a direct reflection of
yourself and your own behavior you see
what I mean so the irony of
sansara the cruelty of this system is
that all your suffering is caused by
being angry and things that aren't there
that's the big what do you call it irony
of life that's the saddest thing of life
if it was somebody evil guy if there was
a devil besides us right if there was a
devil you can blame for everything it'
be all right but the irony the the
saddest thing about
sansar is that uh all the people who
hurt us are are are direct results of
ourselves they are directly coming from
us and we are angry at someone who's not
us we are angry at someone who did not
come from how we act which means we're
angry
at nothing you see we're angry at
somebody who's not there who couldn't be
there see I mean it's not so bad if
there were people running around you
know making bombs or stuff and then you
felt angry at them that would be a I
don't see that would be such a problem
but if you go around getting angry at
people who don't exist now that's a
problem you see what I mean uh that's a
sad thing that's a what do you
call it's just a tragedy that's a
tragedy the suffering of the world is a
tragedy because people are experiencing
the results of karma they have collected
by being angry and things that don't
exist people don't exist got it yes
tomorrow we'll do more more I used up
all your question time I'm
sorry uh I'll sit around at the uh what
do you call those picnic tables under
the thing yeah at dinner okay if you
want
to you know somebody wants to ask me a
question or if you have some question
about your life or something like that
uh like we in our Monastery we spend a
lot of time
studying uh the special connection
between what's happening to you and and
what you're doing you see what I mean
like how you create certain karmas like
uh there are beautiful explanations for
everything in your life every problem
you are having in your life has a
specific Karma behind it and you can
remove it and you can change it uh so if
you have something that if you have
some challenge in your life right now
and and you you want to know what the
seed is and how to get rid
um you we can talk about that or if
there's something you want to achieve in
your life uh how to plant the seed it's
a
very uh beautiful way to spend dinner
okay so and then tomorrow I'll take
questions at the beginning how start all
right if you have any questions and then
we'll keep going deeper
into uh Nirvana and how to get there
there are many many kinds of Nirvana and
we'll talk about some of them tomorrow
right okay uh we have a tradition to
uh give away the Good Karma so if you
know that weird hand thing you can do it
if you don't you can just go like this
and then I'll do a special
prayer which is um to give away the Good
Karma that we collected tonight okay the
Good Karma that we made tonight
[Music]
son
okay thank and like to thank and all the
asham
for their kindness and having us again
year after year and they always treat us
like royalty you're like the only people
in the world who do
that and it's a pleasure to be here and
to learn from you so thank you
[Applause]